<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held at Leicester for that county on the twenty third day of March, 1681/2 by Nathaniel Alsop.</title>
            <author>Alsop, Nathaniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23629</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07869608</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07869608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40176</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25201)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1194:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held at Leicester for that county on the twenty third day of March, 1681/2 by Nathaniel Alsop.</title>
                  <author>Alsop, Nathaniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Carr,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40176:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40176:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE ASSIZES HELD AT LEICESTER, For that COUNTY. On the Twenty third day of <hi>March,</hi> 1681/2.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>NATHANIEL ALSOP,</hi> B. D. Rector of <hi>Church-Langton</hi> in the County of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>S. Carr,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Head</hi> near the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s. 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40176:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40176:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>RICHARD ROBERTS</hi> Eſq; High-Sheriff of the County of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen you pleaſed to lay this piece of Service upon me, of Preaching at the <hi>Aſſizes,</hi> I bethought my ſelf how to diſcourſe ſeaſonably and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably, under the preſent State of Affairs, and at ſuch a general Aſſembly of the Country; and ſoon came to a Reſolution, That to oppoſe ſomething, what my poor Talent could furniſh out, againſt the ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an Epidemical Evil, too viſible upon us, could not be an improper <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking: And certainly he is but an ill Member of the Publick, who at the time when a dangerous Fire appears breaking out, will not bring his Bucket to the quenching of it. If any ſhall except againſt my medling with Political Matters in the Pulpit, they ought to reflect, how our People are of late made all Stateſmen; and that to treat them as ſuch at ſome times, is become neceſſary to their Edification. In the Publick Places of Converſation you ſhall have the Men of Trade arrogate as much Knowledge of Politicks now, as heretofore their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives
<pb facs="tcp:40176:3"/>could arrive unto: So that what is here touched upon as to theſe Matters, is no ways meant <hi>ad Magiſtratum;</hi> I preſume not to inſtruct them therein; but <hi>ad Populum</hi> ſtill: And to rectifie ſome Notions in them, which might have a miſchievous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon Chriſtian Practice, I truſt, will not be thought forreign to the Buſineſs of a Divine. The Sermon hapned to find a favourable Reception with its Audience, and I never intended it ſhould have gone further; but ſome, whoſe Judgments I ought to ſubſcribe unto, thought it might be more ſerviceable, if made more publick; and others, whoſe Authority I ſhall never diſobey, were with ſome Importunities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to have it ſo: And theſe are the true Cauſes of this Publication; whereof I need not inform you, Sir, who your ſelf are my beſt Voucher to the World, for the Reality of this whole Matter. And now, Sir, it begs leave to come forth under the ſhelter of your Name, not only for the common Reaſon of ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications, but chiefly becauſe the ſubject Matter and Deſign of this Diſcourſe requires the Protection of one like your ſelf, whoſe clear and diſintereſſed Zeal for the Publick is ſo exemplary among us. And then the many Favours which I have received from you, bind me to all Opportunities of Gratitude, and to own it to the World how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> Your moſt faithful and obedient Servant, <hi>Nathaniel Alſop.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40176:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EXOD. XX. 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy days may be long upon the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Law of the Decalogue recorded in this Chapter, hath one pre-eminence above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the Scripture; if they were dictated by the Spirit of God, this was alſo written by his Finger; which may ſerve as a <hi>nota bene,</hi> a Hand in the Margin, to direct and engage our Obſervation. That part of it which I have read, is alſo recommended unto us by its ſingular Circumſtances; St. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerves it is the firſt Commandment with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.2. And among the Moderns, <hi>Grotius</hi> notes, how fitly it ſtands in the front of the ſecond Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, agreeably to the method of the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws, which in the firſt place ſecur'd the Sanctity of the Government; ſo this here containing the Nerves and Force of thoſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Laws, which are the preſervatives of Humane Society, deſervedly takes precedence of the reſt. As to the ſenſe and meaning of the words, the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Interpreters and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians do generally conſent, that the duty of Subjects to their reſpective Civil Governours, is more than by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40176:4"/>and Reduction here intended: <hi>Imperium ſancitur, praecipitur obedientia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Melancthon</hi> upon the place: And <hi>Calvin</hi> goes about to aſſign the Reaſon, why a name of Nature is here given to a Political Relation: <hi>It is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to ſoften the ſavage diſpoſition of Man, who is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally impatient of Subjection; to bring the ſtiff-neck, and Iron Sinnew of corrupt Nature, to the yoke of Obedience.</hi> The Truth is what <hi>Zophar</hi> replies to <hi>Job, Man is born like the wild Aſſes Colt,</hi> all reſtraint is againſt the Grain, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one naturally goes big with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and cannot brook a Superior; or elſe, it may be, the tang of our firſt Parents aſpiring, ſtill ferments in the Blood, to be <hi>tanquam dii,</hi> equal to them that are called Gods. It was therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neceſſary conſiderations that St. <hi>Paul</hi> lays his Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Injunction upon <hi>Titus,</hi> the Man of God, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5. to <hi>put them in mind</hi> to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, and to obey Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>It is not enough this be taught and known, but for the great moment of its practice, it ought to be preſſed and inculcated, <hi>put them in mind.</hi> If the Doctrine of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, which is as demonſtrable as any Theorem in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clid's Geometry,</hi> was alſo as much abſtracted from the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and Paſſions of Men, as they are, then might it expect as free and eaſie a paſſage; but when this Nail muſt be driven againſt the inward reſiſtance of Pride, and Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of Envy, Avarice, and Revenge, and ſuch like impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrable Oppoſites; no wonder if a greater Force, and better Skill be required, and repeated ſtrokes: and it were to be wiſhed, that ſome one, a Maſter of Aſſemblies, had undertaken the faſtening of it at this time; in which vacancy the forementioned Cauſes have wrought with me alſo, the meaneſt of my Brethren, to attempt this part of my Office and Duty; eſpecially being ſtirred up with the great
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40176:4"/>and crying Sin of the Times, which is plainly a wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs under the gentle Yoke, a ſurfeiting upon the bleſſings of Government; and I fear there is but too much cauſe to complain, that it is fairly drawing on to an Open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Authority: and who then is ſo hardy, as not to dread the Event? If ſuch provocations as theſe ſhould awaken the Vengeance of Heaven, and move God by his immediate Arm to aſſert the Honour of his own Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Image of our diſtempered State any one may behold in the Glaſs of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> It was at the time when their Supream Governour was one of the meekeſt and moſt merciful Men upon the Earth; it was not long after their deliverance from the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Bondage, where they had ſmarted by the Impoſitions of the moſt cruel Taskmaſters that ever an ingenuous People groaned under; and yet upon every little Diſcontent, if all things went not according to their own Hearts wiſh, immediately they grow ſick of the Government, and <hi>quis eſt iſte Moſes? Why doth this</hi> Moſes, <hi>and the Prieſt his Brother, take ſo much upon them?</hi> They grew weary of Manna, and nauſeated the Bread of Heaven, becauſe it was conſtant, and ever provided for them at hand; but inſtead thereof asked Meat for their Luſts. It was not enough to ſatisfy their natural Appetites, and real Wants, but their wandering Fancies, and their various Diſſenting Pallats muſt be humoured alſo; and upon ſuch diſtates like theſe, they fell into frequent Mutinies and <hi>Aſſociations</hi> againſt the Lord, and againſt his Vice-gerent; inſomuch that <hi>Moſes</hi> was forced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare freely, in that his Farewell-Oration, which <hi>Joſephus</hi> hath left penned unto us, in the Fourth Book of his <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,</hi> That he was more often in hazzard of his Life from them, than from any other of his Uncircumciſed Enemies. I ſhall not ſtay to adjuſt the Circumſtances, nor ſet the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40176:5"/>Members of the Compariſon in joint; but only to ſhew how far we have ſunk from the Rule of our Duty, and ſtill are falling? give me leave to point you back, up as far as to the Source and Fountain of all Political Sanctions, the Baſis of Government, the Cement of Societies, the Princes heavenly, and unforfeitable Charter, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this ſhort Precept, <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. In which Words I ſhall obſerve no more Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, than what are obvious unto every Eye: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Stile or Title here given to the Supream Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, <hi>of a Parent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Debt belonging unto him, <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The enforcement of the Duty by a Promiſe, but with the implication of a ſevere Threat, <hi>that thy days may be long upon the Land,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Stile here is a Name full of Obligation and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearment; we find God himſelf often calling his People to reflect upon it, to hold them faſt to their Duty; <hi>for I am a Father to</hi> Iſrael, ſaith God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.9. <hi>he pitieth as a Father, Pſal.</hi> 103.13. with all the bowels and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that can be ſhewed; <hi>he corrects as a Father, Prov.</hi> 3.12. alwaies within meaſure, and leſs than our Offences deſerve; and upon the ſame ſcore he alſo claims the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of <hi>Sons, Mal.</hi> 1.6. And no doubt but this Title here given to Kings and Sovereign Powers is very apt to move Obedience, to becalm the ſtrivings of the People, and to ſmooth the Yoke of Government, which ſome <hi>Belialites</hi> will always ſpurn at; but what doth <hi>Moſes</hi> then, or rather the Lord himſelf, thus ſpeak unto us, meerly becauſe of the hardneſs of our Hearts? Doth he condeſcend to ſuch mean Artifices, to treat us by the Popular courſes of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, which is wont to ſtroak and ſooth the Beaſt which ſhe deſigns to ride? No, I ſuppoſe the ſoft and endearing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40176:5"/>ſtile here uſed, is more than a Colour of Rhetorick, and ſhall therefore take the occaſion, which is fairly offered, to reflect upon the Original of Civil Government; and the rather, becauſe if it ſhall appear to be founded in the Natural Right of Paternal Authority, as the moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious do affirm, it will prepare the way for that which follows, and the Duty of the Text will be inferred by a neceſſary Logical deduction.</p>
            <p>The ſtile of the Text, being a Name of Nature and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority too, ſuggeſts unto us, in all our reſearches after the Riſe and Birth of Dominion, to have one Eye to the Order and Courſe of Nature: ſo that to underſtand the Original of Civil Power, we muſt aſcend to the true Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of Mankind; and this Method will bring us to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Truth of that Aphoriſm of St. <hi>Irenaeus, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus juſſu naſcuntur homines, hujus juſſu Reges conſtituuntur.</hi> There have been perhaps as many Opinions concerning the Origine of the World, as concerning the Origine of Government, and all of them wide of Truth: But then, as <hi>Tatianus,</hi> from a malicious Adverſary of Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelf to have been converted to the Faith of the Holy Scripture by that ſatisfactory and conſiſtent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which it gives of the Creation of the World; ſo the beginning of Civil Power and Dominion, which the ſame part of Holy Writ accounteth for alſo, if duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, may as well convert the ſeditious underminers of Government, and <hi>turn the hearts of the diſobedient to the wiſdom of the juſt;</hi> when it ſhall appear that it was neither blind Chance, nor ſteep Ambition, nor prevailing Uſurpation, nor Pacts and Covenants, nor any happy Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, nor the longeſt Sword, nor moſt Voices, which made the firſt diſtinction betwixt King and Subject.</p>
            <p>That the firſt common Parent of Mankind was inveſted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40176:6"/>with a Soveraign Power, and acted as Monarch of the World, there are few will queſtion, that will not alſo call in queſtion the Hiſtory of <hi>Moſes.</hi> When <hi>Adam,</hi> who had Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion given him by God over all the Creatures, diſpoſing of his Sons, to one committed the Tillage of the ground, to another the care of the Flocks and Herds, where then was the Equality of Perſons, where the Community of Goods? And if the World was at length peopled by the Offspring deſcended from this Stock, it will be difficult to conceive, how and when ſuch a ſtate of Natural Freedom ſhould be introduced. The great Maſter of Politicks, <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſaw this without his Bible; and although, for want of the Divine Oracles, he was forced to wrap his head in the dark and inextricable Clouds of Eternal Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, yet he ſaw a neceſſity of aſſerting a Natural Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination, where there was a Natural Succeſſion, and came at length to conclude, that the greateſt Kingdom in proceſs of time grew from a ſingle Family, as a large ſpreading Branch ſhoots from a ſlender Stock. It may be the ſtile of Royalty was not heard of 'till the World was well on towards 2000 years old, that came in with the other Trappings and Ornaments, when Monarchy became magnificent and pompous in the Eyes of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but if we look after the Eſſentials of Power, we ſhall find them lodged in the firſt Parent of Mankind, and tranſmitted as an Inheritance by the Firſt-born of the Family. And to deduce this, there is no better Clew than the Sacred Hiſtory it ſelf, which leads us down from <hi>Adam</hi> the Univerſal Monarch, by the Patriarchal Line, unto the firſt Plantation of the World after the Flood, when ſeveral Colonies were led out by their reſpective Heads, and became diſtinct Kingdoms, whereof the Sons or Grand Children of <hi>Noah</hi> were Kings by a Fatherly-Right
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40176:6"/>Right, as appears at large from <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. and among Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authors, moſt accurately from that barbarous Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the end of <hi>Euſebius's Chronicon,</hi> whom for the ſake of the Subject which he handles, the great <hi>Scaliger</hi> thought worthy to be joined with thoſe renowned Pieces of Antiquity. If we follow the Abettors of this Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, and travel farther by the ſame Thred of Scripture Hiſtory into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> we ſhall find there, in a Country of no great Compaſs, above 30 Kings at one time in that little Land. And at this day they tell us, if we look into the ſtate of Affairs in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and thoſe Countries of late and new diſcovery, where they live by the Dictates of ſimple and untaught Nature, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the invented Models of Policy, we ſhall find a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of petty Kingdoms, and the Power of Governing deſcending for many Generations, and no other account but that it ever hath been thus, by a Succeſſion whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning they know not; which ſeems fairly to point up to the Original of Civil Government, and to give us Cauſe from the Premiſes to Conclude, that the Paternal and Regal Authority are the ſame in Nature, not differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Kind, but in Extent only, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Philo</hi> expreſſeth the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>But I deſign no more than the opening and explaining the Notions; it hath been ſufficiently ſtrengthened and guarded againſt all the feeble Encounters made in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it, by a Learned Writer of our own, [Sir <hi>R. Filmer</hi>] in his Obſervations touching Forms of Government; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe the beſt illuſtration of a thing is by ſetting to its Contraries, I ſhall therefore beg leave to glance upon ſome things which are offered by thoſe perſons, who are pleaſed not to admit of this Account of the Original of Government, which in it ſelf is ſo eaſie to be apprehended,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40176:7"/>ſo agreeable to the nature of Things, and Scripture Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſo honourable to God and his Providence, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to the Ends of all Authority and Rule.</p>
            <p>And here, firſt, I cannot but obſerve, how patient and complying our Republicans many times are, that the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean Hypotheſis</hi> ſhould take place; Whether <hi>Promotion comes from the Eaſt or the Weſt, or yet from the South,</hi> they are content, <hi>whatſoever Wind</hi> blows it, ſo that the <hi>Lord</hi> be not in <hi>that Wind;</hi> as wholly unconcerned how things go, as the God of <hi>Epicurus</hi> himſelf, as <hi>Tully</hi> jeers them of old: And all is, only to keep out the ſuſpicion of a Divine Inſtitution in the matter. And indeed it ſeems fully as conſentaneous to Reaſon, that the Fabrick of the World ſhould ariſe from the fortuitous Hit of Attoms, (as that Philoſopher taught,) as that Order and Government, the Strength and Beauty of the Univerſe, ſhould proceed from any thing but the Diſpoſition of a moſt Wiſe Creator. Can theſe Men believe themſelves, who are wont to call upon the People to follow Providence, according to their ſerviceable Doctrine of <hi>Ownings</hi> and <hi>Outgoings</hi> when time was? Or indeed, do they believe any thing of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence at all? who can tell us now, <hi>That God is no more a Favourer of one Family than another, no more than he is a Reſpecter of Perſons.</hi> Nevertheleſs, we truſt that he is a <hi>Reſpecter of Cauſes;</hi> and if the juſt and righteous Claim of any Family or Perſon ſhall engage his Favour at all times, then how much more in the greateſt and moſt weighty Affairs of Mankind? Our Saviour hath taught us, That the very Hairs of our Heads are in the Accounts of Heaven; and ſhall the Crowns of Monarchs be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and forgotten? If there be no Affliction upon a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or People that may be ſaid to riſe out of the Duſt, then ſure an unjuſt and cruel Ruler, which is one of Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40176:7"/>Scourges, is not ſet up by Chance or Fortune; and if not an uſurping Tyrant, who is a common Plague, then certainly no juſt and lawful Prince, who is a publick Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, without the Appointment of God.</p>
            <p>If it be left to Men to conſtitute Governours, it's to be feared, that Fraud or Violence will have the greateſt ſtroke; and that's another way whereby they would have it believed that Empire and Dominion might take its riſe. But this ſure is a very improper Ground whereon to found a juſt and rightful Power, unleſs it ſhould be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly ſo contrived, to leave an Original Flaw in the Conveyance, to the end that Subjection ſhall be always precarious, and, when occaſion ſerves, renounced with a Juſtification.</p>
            <p>Force or Fraud the beginning of Empires! It ſeems ſo jealous are the Party we have here to deal with, leſt God ſhould be thought to have any hand in the matter, that they chuſe rather intirely to aſcribe it to the Devil; for he is the original Liar and Murderer too; And if the way to a Throne be to wade through Blood, and make the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Carcaſes of all Oppoſers ſo many Steps of Aſcent to mount them unto Greatneſs, I ſee not but why every ſuch exalted Head may call him <hi>Father,</hi> whoſe Name in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Deſtroyer, Rev.</hi> 9.7. And then what a hopeful Exerciſe of Power muſt attend ſuch a Beginning? The Sword muſt needs maintain its own Title; and if the Coronation Robes be dyed in Blood, any one may foretell what Complexion Juſtice thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth is like to appear in. An Uſurper brings along with him a neceſſity of renouncing all Humanity, and Religion too: He muſt hate all thoſe whom he hath injured, and muſt puniſh whatſoever his own guilty Fears preſent, as if they were manifeſt Crimes; he muſt tolerate all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40176:8"/>of Diſorder and Confuſion in the Worſhip of Heaven, for the ſake of thoſe which himſelf hath brought upon the Affairs of Earth; he muſt give up the Word of God to mercenary Tongues and unhallowed Hands, to be Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and ſet upon the Rack, till, with the Heathen Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of old, it can <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, cant ſomething in the favour of his Pretenſions. And who can be ſo vain, as even to dream of Property or Liberty under ſuch a State? Who can hope for the enjoyment of a rightful Poſſeſſion, whilſt the Government it ſelf is but a ſplendid Robbery? I ſhall paſs over this Particular, with that Obſervation of the wiſe Hiſtorian <hi>Tacitus, Imperium flagitio acquiſitum nemo unquam bonis artibus exercuit;</hi> which may bear this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>The worſe the Title, the more intolerable muſt the Tyrant be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the Deduction of Government from its true Original, makes ſo fair for the Natural and Divine Right of Monarchy, above all other Forms or Models whatever, hence the implacable Enemies thereof have another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, in which indeed they place their greateſt Strength and Confidence, and that is, by a kind of aukward Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to the Multitude, by a moſt fulſom Flattery of the People, to inſinuate into them an Opinion, That all So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty and Power, all Honour and Authority, as to the firſt Ownerſhip, is theirs, and where they are pleaſed to lodge it. A moſt pernicious Inſinuation, enough to prompt any People to ſeditious Attempts; which, in ſtead of Obedience, (which is the fartheſt thing in their thoughts) only ſets their Heads on work how to recover the Governing Power, which they are told to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held violently from them. Now how diſagreeing this is both to the tenor of Gods Word, and of his Works alſo, we ſhall briefly conſider.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40176:8"/>
            <p n="1">1. To the Word of God. As we find mention but of One ſort of Government there, ſo we find Obedience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preſſed a quite contrary way than is here ſuppoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> as to an Ordinance of Heaven, not a Contract on Earth; as deſcending from above, (ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells <hi>Pilate</hi>) not ariſing from below; the Royal Unction being in this reſpect like that of the High Prieſts, which was ſhed upon <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Head, and did not creep up from the Skirts of his Garment. We never read our Saviour or his Apoſtles en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing the Duty of Obedience upon People from their own Act and Deed, but from the Inſtitution of God, from the Sacredneſs of his Authority, which is ſo cloſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in that of his Vicegerents: St. <hi>Paul</hi> is peremptory in it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>That Governours are ſent unto the People; are Gods Miniſters,</hi> that notes their Original; <hi>for the good and welfare of the others,</hi> there's the End. Nay, the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks of Governours as of Earthly Gods; and would it not be a groſs piece of Idolatry for any People to be the Makers of their Gods? I think we may ſuffer them, as the World now goes, to adore them if they pleaſe; but ſurely they ought to be admoniſhed to hold Hands off, and not preſume as if they could make or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make them at pleaſure. It was a pretty childiſh Conceit, that of <hi>Lucian</hi>'s, which he reports of himſelf, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing young, he was ſet out by his Father to learn the Art of a Statuary, and wondrous jocund and mighty forward he was, having taken great delight in forming little Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Horſes, and other Beaſts, and ſometimes of Men; but that which pleaſed his Imagination moſt, was the hopes and expectation that in time he might carve Gods alſo. I appeal, whether the Multitude are not made ſuch Children, as often as Ambition cringes, and Popularity buys their Breath, contrary to all other ways of Bargain,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40176:9"/>by ſetting a prodigious over-value upon it? The Power of the People muſt be extoll'd, and harangued in their Ears, even to Omnipotency; and they ſo dull, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve at length, that Majeſty it ſelf is nothing elſe but a ſwollen ſtrutting Pageant, which the Breath of their Voices hath extended to that Dimenſion.</p>
            <p>I look upon it as no difficult Undertaking, to ſhew how falſe and groundleſs that Doctrine is, of an Implicit Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in every Kingdom, betwixt God, and the King, and the People; <hi>according to which,</hi> ſay they, <hi>if the King fall away from God, the People may do the ſame to the King.</hi> This is that which <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> and he the firſt of any Man that I know, broacheth in the beginning of his <hi>Vindiciae contra Tyrannos,</hi> and lays down as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of that his Treatiſe. This is the true Mother which hath brought forth thoſe <hi>Covenants, Holy Leagues,</hi> and <hi>Aſſociations,</hi> which have at ſeveral times threatned Confuſion unto Kingdoms: And if ſome Accountants be not out in their Computation, it is a Doctrine which hath ſhed more Chriſtian Blood than now runs in the Veins of living Chriſtians: But I muſt not enter upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion of it at preſent.</p>
            <p>If the Notion of a Popular King be no ways agreeing to the tenor of Gods Word, we ſhall next examine it by the Rule of his Works; and as to its Exiſtence, it will be found there no better than a <hi>Chimera</hi> in Nature. The World, as God made it, acknowledges no ſuch Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Power. When was it, in what Age did the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at firſt conſent thus to make a Deed of Gift of their Natural Freedom? We challenge all true Hiſtories to give us an Account of this matter, and have hitherto had no ſatisfaction. All that hath been found, is, That upon the Diſſolution or Diſmembring of ſome Ancient Monarchies,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40176:9"/>People have been forced to enter upon Agreements and Contracts, and to patch up an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> in ſtead of a juſt Government, and when favourable concurrences fell in, have a conſiderable time continued in that preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſtate; but in this caſe we may ſay as Chriſt did of ſome of the <hi>Moſaic</hi> Diſpenſations, <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo. Plato</hi> indeed among the Ancients is thought to ſpeak pertinently to this matter; that Philoſopher of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers ſomething with a <hi>perhaps,</hi> how ſome Remnants of People might be left upon the tops of Mountains, after a general Inundation, but then it is after his manner of beating dark and doubtful Conjectures in queſt of Truth; and alas it was his ignorance, or at leaſt the want of a diſtinct knowledge of the true Original of Mankind, which forced him and other excellent perſons upon ſuch extravagant Suppoſitions; when as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtart Plato</hi> is the moſt poſitive man in aſſerting, that the firſt Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the World did for ſome time try the Experiment of the brutal life in a Common, like Beaſts in a Paſture, and were driven at laſt by neceſſity to accept of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which to aſſert at this time of the day, (now the Scriptures are unlocked, and in every hand, and the other Records of time have been examined,) is a ſtrange pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption upon Mankind, as if all were Levellers in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. We are ſure and certain, that God ordered all Humane Race to deſcend from one man as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Parent; which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf, who was no great Friend to the Power of Temporal Princes, ſaith is a ſign that God rather approves of the Government of one man than of many. But why may not we uſe it for an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that no other could poſſibly take place, whilſt there was that known ſubordination of Children to Fathers? unleſs there was ſuch a juncture when the Natural Rights
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40176:10"/>of Perſons were ſhuffled and confounded, and it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to make out a Claim to the moſt ancient Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which can never be ſuppoſed at the firſt Plantation of Countries, and beginnings of Kingdoms, when the Earth was peopled by ſeveral Families under their diſtinct Heads, as <hi>Moſes</hi> by Divine Authority doth aſſure us. So that what they ſpeak of an Original Independency, and ſtate of Natural Freedom, muſt be a meer Fiction; or at moſt only an Artificial Suppoſition, to underſtand the force of Contracts and <hi>Common Leagues</hi> made betwixt Equals, but can have no Foundation in Nature.</p>
            <p>There was offered to the World not long agoe, an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis of <hi>Prae-Adamites,</hi> men before <hi>Adam,</hi> upon which a new Syſtem of Divinity was raiſed, and that in the end was found to carry a tendency to Atheiſm and Irreligion; it will concern our Common-wealth Politicians to oblige us with an Hypotheſis of <hi>Praeter-Adamites,</hi> men of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Race and Lineage, who derive not from <hi>Adam,</hi> a Generation like that of the Dragons Teeth in the Poet, where they may find both their ſtate of Equality, and ſtate of War alſo; and when their utmoſt is done, its poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible all may be found to tend to Anarchy and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>But let us, as it becomes good Chriſtians, ſtill adhere to the Word of God; let Holy Scripture, which is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where the adequate Meaſure of our Faith, be here the Rule of our Obedience alſo; the tongue of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels cannot ſpeak more fitly of Soveraign Earthly Princes than it doth; nor more loftily with reſpect to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of their Power, nor more obligingly and with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condeſcention, to ſweeten and engage the Duty of Subjection. Witneſs the expreſſion of my Text.</p>
            <p>And ſo I paſs from the Stile and Title, unto the ſecond thing aſſerted, <hi>viz.</hi> The Duty it ſelf, which was <hi>Honour; Honour thy Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40176:10"/>
            <p>Honour was always accounted as ſomething inherent in the perſon honouring, and ſo it may perhaps ſeem to be altogether at his own free diſpoſal; but the truth is, this may become a Debt as well as any thing elſe, and not to pay it where it is ſuch, is as direct a piece of injuſtice, as to rob a man of any thing which is called his own. <hi>Honour to whom honour,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. where he ſpeaks of rendring unto all their Dues. <hi>If I be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where is my Honour,</hi> ſaith the Lord God. This Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour doth naturally look upwards, and is thought to comprehend all thoſe Duties which Inferiours owe to their Superiours; as Love looks on every ſide, and is called the fulfilling of all the Duties to our Equals. Now if God, who is infinite Perfection and boundleſs Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, be the Object more of our Admiration and Extaſie, which is the exceſs of Reverence, than any thing elſe, then our Honour muſt aſcend in proportion to thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of nearneſs which any Object makes in its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to the Deity, and ſo we ſhall come at length to reſt in that primitive gage which <hi>Tertullian</hi> acknowledges in the Name of the Chriſtians of his time, <hi>colimus Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem tanquam hominem, a Deo ſecundum &amp; ſolo Deo mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem; We honour,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Emperour as a man, but next and immediately unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the full import of the Duty, we may draw it forth in three Notions of the word; <hi>viz. Reverence, Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt is <hi>Eſtimation</hi> or <hi>Reverence,</hi> which is that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the word which bears the ſtamp of common uſage; and this is addreſſed to the Perſon of our Civil Parent.</p>
            <p>The Second is <hi>Maintenance,</hi> which I think is a ſenſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt proper to Holy Scripture, and reſpects his Regal ſtate.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40176:11"/>
            <p>The Third is <hi>Obedience,</hi> with relation to his Laws and Decrees.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not diſcourſe of it in this latitude; ſhould I purſue theſe ſeverally, I muſt of neceſſity intrench too much upon your patience, and the ſucceeding buſineſs of the day: I ſhall therefore confine my ſelf unto the firſt of theſe at preſent, but may chance to conſider it as a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent which is interwoven through the other two, as they ſhall fall in mention.</p>
            <p>But, 1. Honour doth primarily denote the expreſſion of our Eſtimation and Reverence for ſome Excellencies in our Superiours, and can never be ſo fitly placed as when we direct it to our Supreme Governour. It is a ſhame we ſhould have mean thoughts of the Perſon whom God hath thought fit to be his Deputy and Repreſentative up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth; is he worthy to bear the Impreſs and Image of the Almighty's Power and Majeſty, and not deſerving a reverent Idea in our thoughts and minds? There was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Nation that owned a devout ſentiment for their Gods, but paid a proportionable Honour to their Kings, the <hi>Perſians</hi> yielded a Divine Adoration to them both. The Primitive Chriſtians gave Reverence to the very Statues of their Emperours, until <hi>Julian</hi> ſet up the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their falſe Gods by them, with a deſign by that means to trepan them into Idolatry. The Heathens, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, for the Bleſſings of Peace, Plenty, and Protection which they injoyed, thought it not enough to give the higheſt Reverence to their living Princes, but after death, by an <hi>Apotheoſis,</hi> did beſtow a kind of Divinity upon them; and to ſerve and worſhip theſe was the ſum of their Religion. But come we to the People of God, God's own People the <hi>Jews,</hi> and behold there how the holy Oil uſed in their Inaugurations, did by its fragrant odour make
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40176:11"/>the Royal Head on which it was poured, as delightful and dear to them as the <hi>breath of their Noſtrils;</hi> and the morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Prince was lamented among them as the <hi>quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the very Light of Iſrael.</hi> Behold alſo among them, what ſubmiſſion and deference they uſed in their Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to Majeſty, <hi>ſpeak thou unto us, and we will hear, and do it,</hi> is their voice in one place; and it is noted for their uſual ordinary temper, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.36. <hi>that whatſoever the King did, that ſtill pleaſed all the People;</hi> although it's confeſſed, upon the fret and ferment of Sedition they were as turbulent as any; yet never was there a more ſtrict Law given to ſecure the Honour of Soveraign Powers, than God gave unto them, which laid an Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation not only upon the outward man, but upon the words and thoughts alſo, <hi>curſe not the King, no not in thy thoughts;</hi> and certainly with the higheſt Reaſon, for when the Honour of a Prince lies open to be invaded without fear, his Authority is near wounding, and his Perſon no ways ſecure; Reputation both guards his Life, and ſupports his Throne, and they are ever the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Enemies to both, that undermine him in the good opinion of his Subjects, and render him cheap in thoſe Eyes which ſhould look up with the greateſt Veneration; a ſlanderous Tongue is a more ſpeedy Inſtrument of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a Sword of Steel, and a virulent Libel of more certain diſpatch than Gun-ſhot, by how much it is eaſier to reach the Fame of a Soveraign Prince, than to hit his Perſon. In our Judicial Proceedings, the common Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Criminals lies for Offences againſt the Dignity as well as the Crown of our Soveraign Lord the King; reckoning every violation of his Laws may ſtick reproach upon his Government; but there are ſome Offences which ſtrike at the very root of it, the malicious Arts of leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40176:12"/>him before his People, the levelling attempts to lay the Soveraigns Honour firſt in the duſt, knowing the whole Fabrick of the Government muſt follow after it. And theſe are the Crimes which before Earthly Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals deſerve ſevereſt Cenſures of all others, not but that other ſins in ſome reſpects may be found more ſinful at the laſt day, but becauſe theſe are moſt deſtructive of Humane Society, and moſt repugnant to the good and welfare of Mankind: <hi>The Tongue,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James, c.</hi> 3.5. <hi>is a very ſmall Member, but being ſet on fire from Hell;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well warmed with that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſpeaks of, <hi>it can eaſily put the whole courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into combuſtion,</hi> and a ſhort ſpeech may contain that eſſential Poyſon and Rancour of Malice in it, as may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnate the whole Sphere with infection and miſchief. Theſe are uſually the Springs and firſt Movers, which bring on greater Revolutions. And when Confuſion and Deſolation ſhall follow as a Flood, and the Sword ſhall march in Triumph o're the Land, and Ruine like a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whirlewind ſhall throw all into heaps, then if perhaps you look for the kindly Fruits of Repentance from the Authors of ſuch Calamity; all muſt be, only the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of a little improvidence, and that they never expected matters would have run on to that paſs: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is a moſt natural and neceſſary progreſs, from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation of a Government to its Diſſolution.</p>
            <p>And then again, if there be in Scripture a peculiar no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word, to <hi>Honour with our Subſtance,</hi> and if the Holy Ghoſt inſtructs us there, that to ſupply the wants and neceſſities of our Parents be another Branch of the Honour we owe unto them; as our Saviour moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in St. <hi>Mark</hi> 10. and St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo brings it under the ſame head, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. where he informs thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40176:12"/>of their <hi>non-exemption</hi> from Tribute, and implies it to be an act of Juſtice, by his word then uſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ye,</hi> or reſtore, <hi>tribute;</hi> not ſo much a Gift as a Debt. And it is but a very reaſonable return indeed, for our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure nights and our uſeful days, for our peace and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and all the opportunities ſerving unto life and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; I ſay it is but a very reaſonable return, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the neceſſary ſupport of the Government; yet ſtill this ought ſo to be, as in a way conſiſtent with its Honour and Reputation. The Boundaries and Stations of Nature can never be altered, and a contumely offered from a Son cannot be commuted for, by the performance of any other part of his Duty. You will not much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the Obedience or dutiful Regards of that perſon, who ſhall offer to relieve the Neceſſities of his diſtreſſed Father, but withall ſhall read him a petulant Lecture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ill management of his Eſtate, and his ſpendthrift courſes, that ſhall exact accounts with all the rigour and ſcrupuloſity of a Tasker, and tye him up perhaps to ſuch terms and conditions as ſhall be moſt grievous and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom, if not impoſſible. There ſeems to have been more ingenuity, if not leſs wickedneſs, in thoſe Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees of old, whom our Saviour reproves upon this ſcore, in the 7th of St. <hi>Mark;</hi> they fairly daſht out this part of the Divine Law by their own Traditions, and did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude the wants and the expectation of their Parents, with a <hi>Subſidie</hi> in one hand, and a <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> in the other; by their <hi>Vow of Corban</hi> they put an iſſue to the matter, and never let it come to a buſineſs of bargain and ſale be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, or ſuch vile higgling, as can never ſhew with any decency, unleſs betwixt an unbelieving Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and a broking Jew.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:40176:13"/>
            <p>Laſtly, The great and infallible Teſt of our <hi>Honour,</hi> is <hi>Obedience; Then are ye my Diſciples indeed,</hi> ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>if ye do whatſoever I command you:</hi> All our <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna's</hi> and <hi>hails,</hi> without this, are downright mockery. And yet I muſt confeſs alſo, there is a ſort of Obedience which hath little or nothing of Honour in it; that which is forced and extorted by the fear of Penalties, and that which is pickt and choſen for Conveniency, and to ſerve an Intereſt; and ſuch is the reſtive and diſputatious Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which will go not one ſtep farther than a direct Precept of Scripture ſhall preſs it, although it be in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters relating to the Publick welfare, and where there is no Divine Precept to the contrary. The Reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all this may be done where there is no Reſpect had to the Authority of the Law-giver; and it is that alone which gives the formality and true ſtamp to Obedience. Now if many ſhall be found wanting and defective in their Duty, who yet keep the Law, then where ſhall the Diſobedient appear? Nay in what Form of the Kings true Honourers, and right Faithful Subjects, muſt they be placed, who not only violate the Laws, but alſo teach men ſo to do; and teach it not only by Example, but by Precept, by Inſtitutes of Libertiniſm, by diſtinguiſhing men out of their Loyalty, and ſtating of Caſes and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, whereby the Law it ſelf is made the only Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and ſuffers accordingly? Among all the helliſh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations and Devices which the Enemy of Mankind, in the ſhape of an Angel of light, hath hitherto uſed for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Order, and diſturbing the Peace and Quiet of the World, perhaps there hath not been a more dangerous one than that which of late hath appeared among us, and is not unſitly called <hi>The Reign of Conſcience.</hi> I would not be thought to go about to expoſe ſo ſacred a thing,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40176:13"/>whilſt I only expreſs my reſentment of thoſe abuſes, which it ſuffers by the folly and wickedneſs of them who moſt delight to have the word in their Mouths; and it is the greateſt abuſe certainly, to Idolize it, and ſo become Worſhippers of our own ſelves, to aſcribe the ſupremacy and power of determination unto every mans private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which the Law hath placed elſewhere, for a known and publick reſort. The <hi>Oceaniſts</hi> are wont to tell us of an Empire of men, ſo they call Monarchy; and an Empire of Laws, and that muſt be their own dear Common-wealth, but here's an Empire of Conſcience which outs them both. This muſt needs be the moſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary of any other, ſince men have learnt the artifice to manage Conſcience, like thoſe Priſms or Mathematical Glaſſes, which with a ſlight turn ſhall preſent any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which fancy or affection calls for; that Reign muſt alſo be moſt tyrannical, which knows no milder Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for every tranſgreſſion than the pain of damnation; and what Form of Polity muſt we call it, when every man is a King at leaſt, being unaccountable for whatever he doth? If this be the reign of Saints, I ſee not but why the greateſt Senſualiſts in the world may be reconciled unto it; for Conſcience at the moſt, and where it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged with the greateſt ſincerity and truth, is but an act of my own Practical Judgment, which may be corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Intereſt and Paſſion, and as often as by following this I decline from the Rule and Meaſure that is ſet before me, I do in effect make the laſt Appeal unto my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Self. And what is there in the world ſo grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to a proud unmortified Spirit? It's one of the moſt luſcious pieces of Senſuality which any carnal heart can wiſh for; and what can the conſequence be, ſhould it go on, but the evacuating the uſe of the Law, and all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40176:14"/>Proceedings, <hi>i. e.</hi> in ſhort, the ruine of a Kingdom? We ſure, the People of this Nation, above all others in the World have infinite Reaſon to acknowledge it with all gratitude to Almighty God, for aſſigning us our Lot in that Country which of old was called, and ſtill is (would our little Diſcontents but let us know how to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue it) the <hi>Fortunate Iſland,</hi> not ſo much for its tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Climate, but for that happy temper of the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution we now live under, both with reference to the Concerns of our Souls, and outward Eſtate. Our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as to its Subſtance Divine and unalterable, and as to its Mode and Exerciſe is eſtabliſht and ſetled with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of all the Wiſdom of the Nation, and by the Authority of the greateſt Power under Heaven, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be changed or controlled by the Will or Arbitrary Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of any man. The Bounds of our Liberty and Property are ſacred alſo, and not to be invaded, ſo long as there ſhall be any Reverence had to Law or Juſtice among us; we muſt diſſolve this Order, or ſin our ſelves out of the Protection of the Government, before we can be miſerable; unleſs with <hi>Jeſhurun,</hi> growing fat and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, we ſhall run headſtrong down the Precipice of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, nothing elſe can bring it upon us. Nay, we ſeem ſo free from any preſent Grievance, that we muſt call in imagination to help us to anticipate Miſery, and be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht at a dreadful painted Scene, which only our affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fears and Jealouſies repreſent unto us. And next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Almighty God we muſt render unto his Majeſty the Honour due unto him, in all the fore-mentioned Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Duty, for our Peace and Plenty, for our Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Protection from Foreign Enemies, and for the wiſe diverſion of the ſad Effects of our own Animoſities, for the repeated aſſurances of maintaining the Proteſtant
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40176:14"/>Religion, which ſhould be dearer to us than our Lives; for the continuance of His Clemency and Paternal Care over this our Reformed Church, which renders her equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Envy of Papiſts and Diſſenters, but a Sanctuary unto all ſuch as flee unto her, with any ſober Perſuaſions of Religion. And where now are our Returns for theſe Bleſſings, for which the very Heathens would have been building of Altars, and preparing Sacrifices, upon like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion? Whither is our Love and Reverence of Authority fled, or loſt among us? O my Country-men, where is that <hi>Old-Engliſh Loyalty</hi> for which this Nation hath been of old ſo deſervedly renowned? Alas! the <hi>New Plantation</hi> ſeems at length to return the Peſt back again upon us, that was formerly the Sink and Drain into which the noxious Humours of our State were wont to be diſcharged; and now (I know not by what Infatuation) we ſeem to be fond of, and willing to cheriſh them in our own Body; as if <hi>Theſe</hi> could be any Defence to the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe,</hi> which are the profeſt Enemies of the <hi>beſt Proteſtant Church upon Earth;</hi> and if ever the Peace and Settlement of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> chance to be diſturb'd, it will be (in all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Probability) by an Eruption from the Confluence of <hi>Theſe,</hi> when ever they ſhall be ripe for Miſchief: Nay, the freſh Experience of our Siſter-Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> puts it out of queſtion. But bleſſed be God, the Wiſdom and Vigilance of our State is awake, and ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive from what Quarter the Danger threatens; and it's hoped the whole Nation will be ſenſible for what theſe <hi>Coals of Fire</hi> are kept alive and glowing hot within her Bowels, meerly by thoſe <hi>various Winds of Doctrine</hi> which blow from the Caverns of <hi>Schiſmatical Conventicles.</hi> To <hi>theſe</hi> it is our Nation ows her Lankneſs and Ill-thriving under the plenteous Means of Grace and Goodneſs; and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40176:15"/>without Gods extraordinary, abundant, and overflowing Mercy, it's morally impoſſible that the Regular Miniſtry of the Goſpel ſhould have any the leaſt conſiderable Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs upon the Souls of Men among us, under ſuch ſtrong Prejudices, whilſt the <hi>ſtrange Fires</hi> of <hi>Nadab</hi> blazing upon <hi>unhallow'd Altars,</hi> ſhall dazzle and miſguide the <hi>Weak,</hi> and the <hi>Wilful</hi> be ſuffered to perſiſt in the <hi>Contradiction</hi> of <hi>Corah.</hi> If that Paper-Draught and Scheam of an <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which was lately brought to light, be juſtly thought worthy of the <hi>Abhorrence</hi> and <hi>Deteſtation</hi> of every Loyal Heart and Hand, you will not ſpare thoſe <hi>Aſſemblies of Schiſm,</hi> thoſe <hi>Garriſons of Sedition,</hi> which are but ſo many little Models and brief Eſſays of the <hi>Aſſociation in act.</hi> Neither your <hi>Peace</hi> nor <hi>Religion</hi> are conſiſtent with <hi>them.</hi> Our Princes <hi>Power in Eccleſiaſticals,</hi> after the Example of the Religious Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> is one main Article of our <hi>Reformation;</hi> and what a mighty Influence this hath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Civil <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> no Conſidering Man can doubt: <hi>both</hi> which are twice contradicted and everthrown; firſt, by the Fact it ſelf, of <hi>Aſſembling,</hi> ſo notorious and daring, in contempt of Authority; and next, by thoſe <hi>Seditious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> which are but too frequently diſſeminated among them: Nay, if Pregnant Cauſes ſhould not ſometimes miſcarry in their Productions of <hi>evil</hi> as well as <hi>good</hi> Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, ſuch Practices as theſe, ſo ſcandalous to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> perſiſted in, and vouched for, with the Pretences of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Religion, were enough to make the Names of Conſcience and Religion to ſtink upon the Earth. As often as the Language of the proſtitute Preſs, and Common Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Converſation, ſhall be undutiful and reflecting upon Authority, that only argues an ordinary itchy contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Evil running upon the Vulgar; but when the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and Juſteſt Power upon Earth ſhall be confronted with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40176:15"/>a <hi>pretended</hi> Commiſſion from Heaven, and a Publick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Worſhip ſet up, in oppoſition to that which with the greateſt Wiſdom and deliberation is eſtabliſh'd, and <hi>Conſcience</hi> brought to vouch for <hi>one,</hi> which is the ſtricteſt Tie and Obligation to the <hi>other,</hi> this ſhews a Diabolical Contrivance to <hi>ſham</hi> Religion, and make her turn the Point back, and ſtab her ſelf. Yet <hi>this,</hi> and many other Diſtempers we labour under, would meet a ſpeedy Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, were we perſuaded to put the Duty of my Text in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practice. A ſetled Reverence for Authority would breed an Affection to the Perſons of our Governours, and that would produce a Truſt and Confidence in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Management, and this would be a means to baniſh thoſe ill-boading Jealouſies and ſiniſter Interpretations which are put upon every Occurrence, and perhaps is the worſt Symptom of our Miſery. And can there be any thing more equitable, than what is now recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto us, to pay that Tribute of Honour to our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Civil Parent, which is exacted, and not denied, in all other Relations whatever? The Maſter of a Family will not ſuffer his Power of ordering the Affairs of his own Houſe to be diſputed or encroach'd upon by any other; and if it be the Lord of a petty Mannor, how ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute will he expect to be in his little Territories? What a rigid Account ſhall be exacted of thoſe By-Laws which his Worſhip ſhall dictate? and ſometimes ſhall vaunt it more with that one molted Feather of the Crown, and look for more Obſervance, than what himſelf will pay to the Sacred Head which wears the Diadem. One ſhould think the very Love and Senſe of Duty towards our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Lord and Sovereign, ſhould be as prevalent at leaſt with us, as the Dread and Terror of a cruel Uſurper: And ſhall <hi>this</hi> depreſs us to the baſeſt degrees of Servility, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40176:16"/>the <hi>other</hi> not enlarge our Souls with great Propenſions to Honour and Obedience?</p>
            <p>But perhaps there is nothing will make us altogether <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in this great Branch of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but the proper Motives of Religion; and therefore, after the Equity of the thing, let us next conſider what Godlineſs there is in it: And here we ſhall find ſuch a ſtrict Alliance betwixt the <hi>Fear of God</hi> and the <hi>Honour of the King,</hi> that in Holy Scripture they are commonly joyned together, and in Practice can never be divided. The Name of <hi>Piety</hi> is properly given to that Duty which is owing unto Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, by the beſt Claſſical Writers; and the Honouring of a Prince, I have read in a Learned and Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, called an <hi>Elicit Act of Religion,</hi> meaning, I ſuppoſe, ſuch a Worſhip of God, as the Image-worſhip of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> would be, were there no Divine Precept in bar againſt them, rendring their Practice unwarrantable and ſuperſtitious. But we need not ſtrain a Point to that ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cety; If Loyalty be a Duty indiſpenſible, and an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Act of Chriſtian Religion, we have a conſiderable Advantage againſt our Adverſaries on both hands, when we dare joyn Iſſue with them upon the Obſervation of one of the Chief of Gods Moral Laws, as to which our <hi>Papiſt</hi> Adverſaries, and <hi>Diſſenters</hi> alſo, are notoriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective. It's Honour enough, that our Reformed Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been here acknowledged the ſure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatrix of the Principles of Loyalty, and was never wanting in the Practice of them in the worſt of Times; and this is it that makes her the Butt of all the Factions, at which they ſhoot their bitter Arrows: This draws upon her thoſe Loads of Calumnies and Contempts which the Subtile Underminers of the State ſtir up, and unwary Perſons are loud and clamorous in, they know not why:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40176:16"/>Otherwiſe, what reaſon is there imaginable, why ſome that pretend an Agreement in <hi>all Doctrinals</hi> with her, and would go further, ſhould yet labour her Ruine, and would rejoyce to ſee her laid <hi>waſte and deſolate,</hi> but only becauſe ſhe is known to be an impregnable Defence to the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy and lawful Government of the Nation, and cannot, as others do, give a Diſpenſation for Reſiſtance?</p>
            <p>We may ſee it by experience among our ſelves, how the Honour of God is promoted and carried on in the ſame Company, and by the ſame Proportions, with that to the King. Who are they that <hi>frequent the Places where his Honour dwells,</hi> and that <hi>ſet forth the Glory of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Majeſty and Mercy,</hi> by Acknowledgments, Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Confeſſions made unto him, with due Solemnity and Reverence, and make a Conſcience of theſe things? of offering theſe Sacrifices to his Honour, as of old they offered their Goods and Cattel? Are they not ſuch gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally as pay a dutiful Reſpect unto his Repreſentative on Earth? ſuch as are poliſh'd and refin'd by Education, and know the Laws of Obſervance and Regard? And it's agreeable to the <hi>Genius</hi> of a Gentleman, if not byaſſed by ſome Fanatick Intereſt, to aſſert the Publick Rites of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; whereas the Lower Part of Men, eſpecially where they have received any Factious Impreſſions, are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of any the leaſt touch of Conſcience for theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, neither for Gods Honour nor the Kings.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add but few Words more: What remains ſhall be, according to my propoſed Method, to ſhew the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to this Duty, from the Argument contained in the laſt Clauſe of my Text, which is the Promiſe of a very deſirable Bleſſing; but it implies a ſevere Threatning in caſe of Diſobedience, no leſs than an utter Abſciſſion and Cutting off from the Land of Promiſe: And this muſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40176:17"/>needs have a mighty Influence upon <hi>that People</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and all others in general. The force of the Inference lies chiefly in the Threatning. Thus God elſewhere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites them with a gracious Promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.19. <hi>If ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of the Land;</hi> but he drives and compels in the next Words with a terrible Threat, <hi>But if ye refuſe and rebel, ye ſhall be devour'd with the Sword.</hi> The Curſe of God hanging over the Head of a contumacious and rebellious People, is enough to reduce them, if there be any <hi>fear of God in the Place.</hi> This is the proper Seaſon for God himſelf, the King of Kings, to appear and interpoſe, when his Vicegerents here on Earth ſhall be ſet at nought: Here is <hi>dignus vindice modus,</hi> a proper Care for the All-ruling Providence, and a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence worthy of a Divine Revenge; and it hath ſeldom failed upon ſuch Exigencies, although it hath been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſlow. I ſhall leave but one Example with you; but it is ſuch an one as I think we may challenge all Hiſtory, Sacred and Humane, to match it; it is in the 16th. of <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> in this very People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and not far from the time when this Law was given them. At the beginning of the Chapter <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company riſe up againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Chief Magiſtrate and Chief Prieſt, As <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> are ſtill found in Conjunction, ſo the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Prieſt</hi> have the ſame Common Enemies. And what was the Cauſe that ſtirred up theſe Men to mutiny? It was plainly the <hi>Levellers</hi> Grievance, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity of Gods People, the hated Eminence of a Superior, and the heavy Yoke of Government: For thus they vent their Diſcontents againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Congregation are holy, every one of them; wherefore then lift ye up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi> Here's now the Maſque of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40176:17"/>with all its Paint and Varniſh on: It is the <hi>Lords Cauſe;</hi> it is for <hi>freeing</hi> the Congregation of the Lord from the <hi>Slavery,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> held them under, for aſſerting the <hi>Liberties</hi> of an <hi>Holy People:</hi> And as if the meer joyning with the <hi>Faction</hi> had been <hi>Holineſs</hi> it ſelf, it is alledged, <hi>they were all holy, every one of them. Moſes</hi> looks upon this Face of Affairs as of a dangerous preſage, and makes his Appeal to God, the Ordainer of Powers, and the Reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Kings; he joyns Iſſue with the Mutineers upon the Point, and is content the Divine Right of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be tried by the Succeſs which God ſhould give to the Sacrilegious Enterpriſe of theſe Men. And what was the Event? Why, the Queſtion under debate received a dreadful Deciſion, by the Overthrow and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Rebels; and the Righteous God deſcrib'd as it were the Nature of their Sin, by ſome Lines of the Puniſhment, as appears by the Sequel of the Story. Here is now an Example of Gods appearing for his own Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution: and let any one of them who have uſed to talk ſo loud for Gods <hi>owning their Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>Outgoings with their Arms,</hi> match it if they can. It's confeſs'd, in common Proceedings, and the ordinary Courſe of Providence, an Argument from Succeſs is very fallacious; but in the Caſe as it was here, when the very Point under Trial was the <hi>Divine Right of Superiority and Rule,</hi> and this put upon the Iſſue, to be maintained by God by Miracle, or elſe to fall; and when God ſhall anſwer to the Appeal in ſuch an extraordinary manner; here, I take it, in ſuch a Caſe as this, Gods Works are as inſtructive and infallible as his Word; and in all ſuch Events we may ſay, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Magicians did, <hi>This is the Finger of God;</hi> a Finger by which he writes his Will unto us as plain and legible, as ever he did upon the Tables of Stone to <hi>Moſes;</hi> as legible
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40176:18"/>as is the Precept it ſelf, for whoſe ſake I have alledged this Example.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, <hi>knowing the terrors of the Lord,</hi> let us all, my Brethren, be perſuaded and exhorted to have a care that we never provoke Almighty God, by our cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sins, to ſend forth his Judgments any more upon this People and Kingdom. Let us, who value our ſelves in being thought the Loyal and obedient Subjects, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by a godly and upright Converſation to redeem the Profeſſion of Loyalty from the evil Slanders of ſuch as ſeek occaſion to reproach it: Let us ſerve and honour our King with the greateſt Zeal and Duty that we owe, but our God infinitely more: Let us endeavour to live, as far as is poſſible, without the <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> of Vice, as well as free from its <hi>contagiou;</hi> that ſo we may break and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit that moſt falſe, ill-natur'd, and uncharitable <hi>Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> which the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites</hi> of the Times have taken up, when they ſet the Kings <hi>Loyal Subjects</hi> on one Hand, and the <hi>Sober Godly Party of the Nation</hi> on the other. And let them who have been defective in this kind, ſhew forth the <hi>Fruits of Repentance,</hi> having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd a <hi>Pardon</hi> and <hi>Indempnity</hi> for their Crimes paſt, let them learn at length to be ingenuous, and, if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to convert their Rancour into Duty; let them but <hi>begin now</hi> to love, honour, and obey the King <hi>much,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>much hath been forgiven them:</hi> Let them never caſt a Thought back upon <hi>Aegypt,</hi> or its <hi>Fleſh-pots,</hi> nor chew the Cud upon thoſe luſcious Morſels of Rapine and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege, which, for the eaſe and health of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, they have been forced to diſgorge: And above all, let them ever mind it, not to relapſe into their <hi>old</hi> Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of <hi>turning Faith into Faction, and Religion into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40176:18"/>From which, and all the Plagues and Puniſhments attending it, Good Lord deliver us, by the Merits of thy dear Son; To whom, with thee, and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour aſcribed, the Kingdom, Power, and Glory, for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
